Guide to the George Borrow Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
George Borrow collection
1833-1862
GEN MSS 324
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.9
(2 boxes)
Collection includes various manuscripts of poems and essays by Borrow; manuscripts of translations by Borrow of poems by Vincenzo da Filicaia, Claus Frimann, Dafydd ap Gwilym, Duncan Ban MacIntyre, and Goronwy Owen; and one letter from Borrow, probably to John Murray, publisher of Borrow's "The Romany Rye."
Borrow, George, 1803-1881
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Source information is recorded on the folders. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to George Borrow, acquired by the library from a variety of sources. Materials incorporated into the collection prior to October 1997 have been organized into one series, Papers.
Poetry; Dafydd ap Gwilym, active 14th century; Borrow, George, 1803-1881; Filicaia, Vincenzo da, 1642-1707; Frimann, Claus, 1746-1829; MacIntyre, Duncan Ban, 1724-1812; Murray, John; Owen, Goronwy, 1723-1769?
- Papers, 1833-1862; Series I; 0.4' (1 box)
  - ALS to an unidentified recipient [John Murray, publisher of Borrow's The Romany Rye ?], [No place, probably London], [ca. 1857] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Beowulf", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes typed transcript
    Acc #: 641231-d
  - "The Death of Napoleon," autograph manuscript of two versions of a poem, [n.p.], n.d.
    Published in The Works of George Borrow, ed. by Clement Shorter, London, 1923. v. 9, p. 26-29
  - "The Fox," autograph manuscript translation of a poem, [n.p.], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    From the Welsh of Dafydd ap Gwilym. Published in The Works of George Borrow, ed. by Clement Shorter. London, 1923. v. 8, p. 267-8
  - "Gypsy Scenes," autograph manuscript poem of 28 stanzas of 4 lines each, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Begins: "O wife, beseech the prison lord ..." Published in The Works of George Borrow, ed. by Clement Clement Shorter (Norwich Edition) London, 1923, vol. IX, p. 160-164
  - "Here at hame ..." 13 lines in Borrow's hand (Box 1, Folder 5)
    In wrapper labelled: This looks like a fragment of MacIntyre's ode to Ben Dourain which is mentioned in Wild Wales. Ch. 18
  - "Hertugen Af Skage (The Duke's Daughter of Skage)," translation in Borrow's hand, with typewritten transcript (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Danish ballad
  - "History of James Allan," autograph manuscript, with typewritten transcript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Acc #: 690410-b
  - "In the eighteenth hundred year," translation in Borrow's hand (Box 1, Folder 8)
    [Beginning of poem] fragment from the Romany[?]
  - "Letter of the flying," translation in Borrow's hand (Box 1, Folder 9)
    [Beginning of poem] fragment of a Danish or Old Norse poem. With notes on Northern poetry
  - "Ode to Horneel," autograph manuscript of two versions of a translation, from the Norwegian of Claus Frimann, [n.p.], 1833
    Accompanied by two copies of a note about the author in Borrow's hand. Printed in The Works of George Borrow, ed. by Clement Shorter. London, 1923. v. 8, p. 129-138
  - "Parchments with age all dusty and dim," autograph manuscript poem (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Fragments. [Borrow's note]: Part of a poem relating to the Danish historian Saxo Grammaticus; 6 lines from Oehlenschlaeger's St. Hansaften. Translation in Borrow's hand
  - "The Pedigree of the Muse," autograph manuscript poem of 126 lines, from the Welsh of Goronwy Owen, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Begins: "Ole Homer, Grecian bard divine ..." Printed, with many variations, in The Works of George Borrow, edited by Clement Shorter (Norwich Edition) London, 1923, vol. VIII, p. 307-311
  - "Rabbi Benjamin Bar Jona of Tudela," autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    "The ms was bought by Dr. [George Alexander] Kohut from G. Michelmore Co., London, some time around 1924, for $120. It is catalogued as no. 45 in P. P. Levertoff's Notes upon an important collection of Hebraica. London, [1924]. Levertoff dates the ms circa 1886." - L. Nemoy
  - "The Sharp-Tongued Lady," autograph manuscript poem of 2 stanzas of 4 lines each, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Begins: "Oh Sophy, 'tis your vile abusive tongue ..." Printed in The Works of George Borrow, edited by Clement Shorter (Norwich Edition) London, 1923, vol. IX, p. 247
  - "Sir Truel's Daughters," translation in Borrow's hand (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Fragment of the Danish ballad
  - "Song," from the Gaelic [?], translation in Borrow's hand (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "Song as if made by one girl on another. From the Gaelic of MacIntyre," translation in Borrow's hand (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Acc #: 630322-a
  - "Songs of the East," autograph manuscript, n.d.
    Bookplate of Mary Pinkerton Carlisle
  - "Sweden." Autograph manuscript essay with corrections and revisions (Box 1, Folder 17)
    On Swedish history and literature
  - "Taillefer, from the Norman French," autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Also includes Borrow's copy of part of the original "Roman de Rou" and manuscript poem, "To the Spider"
    Acc #: 601216-c
  - "The Wandering Children and the Benevolent Gentleman," autograph manuscript poem, [n.p.]
    Published in The Works of George Borrow, ed. by Clement Shorter, London, 1923. v. 18, p. 237-9
  - "The Welsh and their Literature," autograph manuscript of portions of an essay, [1861] (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Published as an article in The Quarterly Review, 1861 Jan, p. 38-63
  - Wild Wales, autograph manuscript of parts of various chapters of the book, [1862?] (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
    Including the poems "Lines on a spring," "Poverty and riches" (early draft), and a translation of Filicaia's sonnet on Italy. Wild Wales was first published in 1862
- Oversize, 1833, n.d.; 1.5' (1 box)
  Oversize contains materials from the Papers series, arranged in the order in which they appear in the series
  - "The Death of Napoleon," autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 22)
  - "Ode to Horneel," autograph manuscript of two versions of a translation, 1833 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 23)
  - "Songs of the East," autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 24)
  - "The Wandering Children and the Benevolent Gentleman" autograph manuscript poem (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 25)